Guide to the General John J. Pershing letters, 1917-1936 MS 161
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
General John J. Pershing letters
1917-1936
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Pershing, John J. (John Joseph)
MS 161
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder)
Letters written by General Pershing on both personal and official business.
Biographical Note
John J. Pershing was born September 13, 1860 in Laclede, Missouri. Having graduated from West Point Military Academy in 1886, he fought in the United States military in the Spanish-American War and several Indian Wars. He also served as brigadier general in the Philippines from 1906-1913 and led the attack against Mexican rebel Pancho Villa in 1916. Early in his military career, he served with a black regiment, giving him the nickname Black Jack. For a time, he also taught at West Point.
In 1917 when the United States declared war on Germany, Pershing was chosen to command the American troops in Europe. Pershing can claim two significant victories: the attack on the German's Saint-Mihiel line of defense and the Meuse-Argonne operations, a month after which the Armistice was signed.
Upon returning to the United States, he was given the rank of general of the American armies. For three more years he served in the military as chief of staff until his retirement in 1921.
General John Joseph Pershing passed away on July 15, 1948 in Washington D.C.
Scope and Contents
Letters written by General Pershing on both personal and official business. Correspondents include Earl of Derby, Mrs. Kingsley Ohl, Hon. Louis C. Crampton, Dr. Clarence J. Owens, Mrs. James C. Frazer, General Calcer C. Sniften, Reverend Alton M. Young, Lieutenant Col. George Grosman, Col. Hugh J. Gallagher, John A. Stewart, Josephine Patten, Paul Maerker Branden, and Mr. Wheeler.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
Purchase
General
The abbreviations included included in the list of letters have the following meanings: ALS = handwritten letter, signed by the author and TLS = typewritten letter, signed by the author.
Index Terms
Subjects
Military; World War (1914-1918)
Document Types
corrrespondence
Subjects (Persons)
Pershing, John J. (John Joseph)
- Series I: General John J. Pershing letters, 1917-1936, 11120
  - 1917 June 22: John Joseph Pershing (JJP) to Earl of Derby (TLS), 11144 (Folder 1)
  - 1919 January 17: J.J.P. to Mrs. Kingsley Ohl (TLS), 11143 (Folder 1)
  - 1919 March 11: J.J.P. to Hon. Louis C. Crampton (TLS), 11142 (Folder 1)
  - 1920 March 10: J.J.P. to Dr. Clarence J. Owens (TLS), 11141 (Folder 1)
  - 1920 March 19: J.J.P. to D.C.J.O. (TLS), 11140 (Folder 1)
  - 1920 July 17: J.J.P. to Mrs. [J. Kingsley] Ohl (ALS 2 letters), 11139 (Folder 1)
  - 1920 December 13: J.J.P. to Dr. Clarence J. Owens (TLS), 11138 (Folder 1)
  - 1921 September 11: J.J.P. to Mrs. James C. Frazer (TLS), 11137 (Folder 1)
  - 1921 December 7: J.J.P. to General Calcer C. Sniften (ALS 2 letters), 11136 (Folder 1)
  - 1922 January 27: J.J.P. to Reverend Alton M. Young (TLS), 11135 (Folder 1)
  - 1923 January 30: J.J.P. to Lieutenant Col. George Grosman (TLS), 11134 (Folder 1)
  - 1924 September 15: J.J.P. to Colonel Hugh J. Gallagher (TLS), 11133 (Folder 1)
  - 1925 March 26: J.J.P. to Annulet A. Ohl (TLS), 11132 (Folder 1)
  - 1925 December 22: J.J.P. to John A. Stewart (TLS), 11131 (Folder 1)
  - 1926 March 8: J.J.P. to Josephine Patten (TLS), 11130 (Folder 1)
  - 1928 February 6: J.J.P. to Brig. General C.C. Sniften (TLS), 11129 (Folder 1)
  - 1931 October 10: J.J.P. to Annulet A. Ohl (TLS), 11128 (Folder 1)
  - 1932 July 2: J.J.P. to Paul Maerker Branden (TLS), 11127 (Folder 1)
  - 1933 May 11: J.J.P. to Mrs. Hugh J. Gallagher (TLS), 11126 (Folder 1)
  - 1935 May 14: J.J.P. to Mrs. Kingsley Ohl (TLS), 11125 (Folder 1)
  - 1936 January 10: J.J.P. to Col. and Mrs. Hugh J. Gallagher (TLS), 11124 (Folder 1)
  - [year unknown] December 15: J.J.P. to [Josephine] Patten (ALS 2 letters), 11123 (Folder 1)
  - [year unknown] December 19: J.J.P. to Mr. Wheeler (ALS), 11122 (Folder 1)
  - [year unknown] December 19: J.J.P. to Mr. Wheeler ALS, 11121 (Folder 1)